Let's say you have seen a job
opening in LinkedIn and you like
that job and you want to send a cold
email to the HR regarding the job
opening
So what will many people do?
They will open ChatGPT and they
will put a prompt something like
this
Write an email to HR at OpenAI about
senior AI engineer job opening and I
want to apply and click on enter
And what will ChatGPT do?
It will give you the basic generic
answer
Senior AI engineer application,
there is no high recruiter name and
very small email and would you be
open to 15 minutes screening call?
If you send an email like this,
do you think recruiter will be
impressed and they will call you
back?
No, right? For the same task,
we will give a different prompt.
Let's see what will happen
So this is a prompt, I will explain
the prompt later on, not right now
and let's enter
Now look at the output,
ChatGPT will take some time
Senior AI engineer production rag
and agent systems, Hi Archana,
there is a name here
I saw senior AI engineer opening,
focus on long term horizons and what
are my skills? Why am I applying for
this job?
And after that, I am asking for 15
minutes screening call and also I
need to provide my link to the
LinkedIn and resume as well
So what are
we
doing here?
So in both, same ChatGPT and same
model but the output difference is a
lot when you consider about cold
emails
So if you look at this prompt,
there are a lot of roles,
context, audience, preferences,
tasks, length and constraints
And this is what an actual prompt
should be and this is how you will
build your prompt
So how to build these prompts for
your specific task is called
prompt engineering
In the next 20 minutes,
I will teach you everything step by
step on how to build that prompt
If you want to build a good
production level prompt,
you need to follow 5 steps
1st step is the skeleton,
2nd step is the constraints,
3rd step is the few short examples,
4th step is the decomposition
And 5th step, I will teach you at
the end of this video
So before we learn those 5 points,
let's clear one simple doubt
You might have a question in your
mind, when will I go to ChatGPT,
will I get a prompt?
And I get a perfect answer,
right?
Then what is the need of prompt
engineering?
You are absolutely right
Otherwise, the correct answer that
comes when you give a simple prompt
is
Behind that, open AI developers are
doing a lot of prompt engineering
What happens is, in the backend,
they will build all of these things
What is hidden system prompt?
They will convert your single line
into a prompt template
They will put custom instructions,
what to do, what not to do
How does ChatGPT remember your
details?
Because of prompt
Along with that, the last 10 -20
messages
You need to know the context of the
conversion to ChatGPT
And along with that, any attached
files or images
And then, what is your actual
question?
After doing all this, they will
build this entire prompt
And that prompt is what we call it
How did prompt engineering come?
And after taking all that prompt and
going to ChatGPT
You get a perfect answer
That's why, sometimes even if you
write a smaller prompt
You feel that ChatGPT is
providing very good answers
Why?
In the backend, all of the
developers are doing the complete
prompt engineering
You can't see that
Even ChatGPT, Claude,
gemini, everyone does this
So now, let's take a real example
What is this?
Now what you need to do is
You are building an application
And in that application,
you need to add an AI feature
To add that AI feature
Let's say, you will go via API call
For ChatGPT, Claude,
gemini
How will you do that API?
You will call like this
But in this, there are all the steps
we have done
You need to handle all of that
If you don't know prompt engineering
How are you going to handle all of
those things?
So by doing a basic API call like
this
If you get any issues
You will find no system hidden
prompts
And then no memory, no conversation
No safety defaults
And because you don't have prompts
You will get a huge costing
In my previous video, we explained
Why some people get huge amount of
bill
And why some people get less amount
of bill
Because of prompt as well
This is also one of the factors
And that is why
Learning prompt engineering
To build agentic level production
systems
Is very mandatory even in 2026
Here is a question that I want you
to think about
You have given a task
But what does the AI know about you?
You don't know who you are
You don't know what you will do
You don't know who will see the task
output
It knows nothing about you
You don't know what output you want
You don't know what kind of output
you want
Isn't it?
Based on the prompt
It will only guess the answer
And when you guess the answer
The answer will be too generic
To fix that problem
Let's discuss about the first topic
The skeleton
There are 5 parts in this skeleton
The first part is role
Now we have LLM
How that LLM should act
May be a doctor
May be a senior developer engineer
May be a backend developer
May be a full stack engineer
Anything you need to provide the
role
Along with that you need to provide
context
What did I do till now?
I am writing a cold email
To write such an email
I need to provide what is the job
that I am applying for
And what are my resume details
What is my project
So all of that context
The email will be personalized
That is the second part
And the third part is the task
Now we have the role
Now we have the context
Now this LLM
Whether it is ChatGPT,
Gemini or Claude
What is the actual task
What should it do
You are providing a task
And after that the format
Means
After completing that task
You will get the output
Which format should that output be
in
May be sometimes you want the output
in JSON format
May be sometimes what you need
You want the output in the email
Sometimes you want the output in the
image
Or audio or video
So your format is also important
Along with that the length
Sometimes Claude if you used it
It will provide detailed
documentation
I don't need that much documentation
So I also need to specify
What should be the output length
These are the five core pillars
That will make any prompt beautiful
instantly
So what is our example
We have a bad prompt
What is that prompt
Write an email to HR at OpenAI
About the senior AI engineer job
opening
That I want to apply
So if I write such a prompt
I will give a rating of 2 out of 10
Now such a prompt
What should we do to make it good
We need to apply all of these five
rules
What is the role
Context, task, format and length
Now let me show you an example of
the same thing
See now we have a bad prompt
How to make it better
So starting role
Means you are an AI engineer with
five years of production experience
Writing a cold email to a recruiter
Confident, specific and not
desperate
This is the role we assign to our
LLM
After that context
In this context
Who is the audience
What is our goal
Along with that the reference
What is the reference
What is the job description that I
am applying for
And along with that what are my
skills
Maybe I can even put my resume as
well here
Otherwise I just put a flagship
project
And after that
The third part
Which is the task
What is this task
Write a cold email to HR recruiter
for this role
After that our format
How should the format be
Subject line should be within 15
words
Should be specific, no cliché
After that you should greet
In that greeting I gave the name
Hi Archana
That's why in our first output
Archana's output came
Not dear hiring manager
Because I want the email to be very
personalized
Along with that body
Short
Crisp
You need to showcase my project
In the star approach situation
After that there should be one clear
ask
What is this
Should have a 15 minute screening
call at least
And then sign off
And the total output should be
within 300 words
So what we are going to do now is
We will copy this same prompt
Take that prompt
We will put it in the chart GPT
And let's see what the answer is in
that chart GPT
Let's see
See I copied the same prompt
And see
Hi Archana
And some emojis came here
Which is not good actually
And I hope you are doing absolutely
amazing
And have a wonderful day
If you get such a mail
Do you think HR is interested
In looking at the mail
Starting
Mood off right
Because it is like A generated
Situation, task, action result
And various emojis came
Which is fine
Considering if we compare it with
bad prompt
But even then
There are a couple of things which
we don't like
Isn't it
What is in it
Emojis
A little more length
Even though we put length as 300
But that is fine
And I don't want this
I hope you are doing well
And there are hyphens here and there
So same model same task
Just a five different
Techniques
The output becomes five X
Better
Everything is fine
But there are a couple of things
Which you don't like at all
So how we can make this
Output even better
So that is where we will talk
About the next concept
Which are called constraints and
negatives
Now our output has come
There are a lot of mistakes in that
output
These emojis
I hope you are doing well
Now to eliminate this
What you do is
You use a keyword called
Constraints
In those constraints
You will define
You don't need any response
From the ChatGPT
That is very important
See
No I hope this email finds you well
No I am writing to express my
interest
No emojis at all
No hyphens
No begging tone
No listing of generic qualifications
Pick one
And don't add or assume anything
We can add more constraints
So what a lot of people think
Is that after this output
No response is coming
You need to also enforce
That you don't want any output
You need to specifically tell to the
AI
And one more thing is
Please make this thing better
There is no need to say please
Because AI is just a tool at the end
What you need to do
You need to be direct
The phrase do not
Is more powerful than please avoid
Because you are giving
Crystal clear commands to the LLM
And one more thing is
In production we use pick one
And generic qualifications
Why?
When there is pick one
What it does is
Analyze the important topics in our
JD
Analyze the bullet points in our
resume
And based on all the extra
Matches
It writes cold emails
That's it
I am an expert in 5 -6 different
technologies
I won't add everything
Because what is our end goal?
You want as much better cold
Email as possible
For that you need to personalize
Using the prompt
Now what we are going to do
Let's go back to our prompt
And in this prompt
Let's also add
All of these constraints
After adding these constraints
Now let's look at
What is the output that we are going
to get
From the chat GPT
I am providing the same prompt
Now let's look at the output
Senior AI engineer
Rag production systems
And this output
Is much better
Hi Archana
I noticed senior AI engineering
opening
And the emphasis on agentic systems
Retrieval and reliability at scale
I built this in one of the bus
It is providing the exact
Project that I did
With the numbers as well
After reading this paragraph
The recruiter knows what are my
capabilities
And at the end
We are requesting if you like to
have more
Conversations let's jump on a call
for 15 minutes
See now this
Looks like a proper cold email
So by adding
These constraints
We are getting the output
The way we want
But here
We can make this even better
That is like
What if you already
Wrote a cold email
And you know some of the cold emails
Got worked
You have the email which is
Working in the real time
So what you can do
You can give those as an example
Close to the LLM
So that is where
We call it the next technique
Which is called few short learning
Imagine
I have hired you
For content creator
So your first job is
To write a script for my next video
So what do you do first
You come to me and ask for my old
video script
Right?
Because your ideology
Your way of thinking is very
different
From what I am doing actually
Yes?
So now you see my old script
And you will reshape your output
According to my needs
Yes?
So that same thing
It is called few short learning
So when you give a prompt to an LLM
Without leaving the output
Maybe
Provide some examples
Okay? So example intent
Let's say examples of the style
That I want
Subject should be like this
And mail should be like this
So like this
If you provide one example
That is called one short
If you provide two examples
That is called two short
If you provide three examples
That is called three short
And if you provide few examples
That is called few short
Very simple
The idea is
You already know
This will work
You are just feeding that content to
the LLM
Such that
Your next output should also
Follow this way
Very simple
Now let's go and pick the same chart
Into chart GPT
And let's look at the output
This may be even better
For my personal use case
Because I already like
An example that I gave in few short
So the idea is
To put a couple of examples
Which you think are really
Working good for you
Such that the LLM will follow that
Now based on
All of the things that we have done
The prompt we wrote
Almost 9 out of 10
Rating
So what did we do first?
We wrote a single line of prompt
Then we have this much number of
lines of prompt
For the same task
This is what we call it
As a prompt engineering
We are building one layer
On top of other
To make a very good prompt
Such that LLM can reproduce
The same kind of output
Every single time
And guys here is one more example
Of how I use few short
In my day to day life
For my video scripts
I need to write hook
So what I will do is
I will show some hooks
That I have already used
In a sync AI agent video
I used this hook
In a video called LLMs are built
In a video called how to control
ChatGPT
I used this hook
So based on these 3 kind of
learnings
With my personal examples
I am generating 3 more hooks
For 3 different topics
Then what does ChatGPT do?
It will go and understand
The style, the voice, the narration
Every single thing
And it will generate 3 more hooks
In that space
See hook A, hook B
And hook C
Every video gets 3 different hooks
Based on 3 different styles
Now I just need to choose it
Very simple
Now the output we get is
90 -95 % perfect
With our prompt
But in some situations
What happens is
You need to have a lot of tasks
To be done
In that case
What happens in a single prompt
It will not perform that much
Productively
For example let's say I want to
record a video
I will give task to an agent
What?
I need to do a video on a topic
So what should the agent do?
It needs to do a research
Then it needs to write a script
It needs to evaluate the code
written in the script
Then it needs to write
Detailed line by line script
It should provide me
Thumbnails
It should provide me documentation
It should provide me description for
the YouTube video
And every single thing
So many tasks
In a single prompt
Do you think it is better?
It could be
But my personal opinion is
When you are working in production
level systems
It is better to
Separate every task
Into their individual prompts
And that is where
The next chapter comes into picture
Which is called task
Decomposition
So this decomposition
Is called chain of prompts
Now we have a task
What? Find the match
In our JD
What matches our skills
Give that to a separate prompt
Another one is
Draft star email
How to form my project
Into a star approach
That is a separate prompt
After that
I want to generate a final
Polished output
That is my third prompt
So you might think
Is it necessary to do this for a
simple task?
You are absolutely right
For simple tasks
There is no need to do this
But what if you are doing
Something very large
So let's say
One example is
In our company
You are migrating your dashboards
From the table to the Amazon quick
site
So what do you do?
You need to extract the intent
Of the table
You need to extract data sets
You need to extract calculations
Transformations
Like this
For every step
You write different prompts
And take the output from every step
And finally
You will try to migrate
So when you write at production
level
It is better to break it up
Into smaller chunks
Such that every prompt
Will tackle exactly one problem
Without any deviations
So this is called
Chain of thought
Otherwise
There are some models
GPT 5.5
OPUS 4.7, 4.8
They are already
Reasoning models
By default
When you give a prompt
Because they are on the thinking
Models
They are enabled with chain of
thought
By planning step by step
They will start executing the tasks
So the last thing
You need to specifically mention
Think step by step
Now you don't need to do all of
these things
But even now
If you are using older models
Let's say 5.4 mini
Via API
Then mentioning
Think about step by step
By writing a line
Your output will become even better
So this is what we call it as
Task decomposition
And now for the secret step
Which is called
Interview style prompting
So let's say
You don't know any of these
techniques
You just need to understand
I know a simple English line
And I want to give that prompt
What you can do is
You can just put your prompt
Along with that
I will provide this
Before you write anything
Interview me
Ask me one question at a time
About anything you need
Whether it is JD, background,
project
Audience, tone
Format, constraints
Examples
After each answer
Ask the next question
What are you doing here
I have a single line of prompt
But to write a better answer
I don't need ChatGPT
So I am asking ChatGPT
Ask me what you need
I am saying I will give
Let's see what happens
So great
I will interview one question at a
time
Now what I am asking is
What is the strongest project
That you have done showcased in the
email
So project name, company,
problem
What you built, text pack,
scale
Measurable results
So what I am doing is
I will provide the details about my
strongest
Project
So this is the first question
Ok that is done
Then it is asking second question
For this open AI role
What is the strongest AI,
LLM
Agentic project that you have built
I just need to provide even more
information
So what I will do is
Let me give you one more information
And after that
Let's see
Question 3 about rag
What will I do after that
I will provide third project
I will provide some details
Ok now let's see
Excellent this is good
Question 4 what is your goal
What is our goal
I want to get the recruiter
screening call
Let's say that is my goal
And question 5
Do you already know the recruiter's
name
Let's give Archana
And I want to have a professional
And confident technical tone
I don't want anything which is not
good
Now based on all of these
Inputs that I have provided
It is giving me the output
So what we have done
In the beginning
We only know this in prompt
But for ChatGPT
Or any LLM
What details do we need
We are asking ChatGPT
Or LLM to ask us
Like an interview
And for every question you are
providing answer
At the end you got the output
Which we liked in the initial part
So either you can do like that
Or you can do like this
From the beginning
There are all the techniques
The prompt building
Where you can use it
When you are talking via APS
In your company
When you are building the projects
You have to give direct prompt
It will not be a question and answer
But if you are learning this stuff
Interviewing something like this
Is the best technique
Let's say you gave me a job in the
office
I don't know what to do
What will I do
I will go as a LLM
I will ask
I want to achieve this task
Ask me or interview me
What are the topics I need to learn
And in every topic I will interview
So I am learning a lot
While talking to these LLMs
So almost 90 % of the prompt
engineering
You have done
So before we close this call
I want to show you the final prompt
template
So what is the role
What is our context
You can put anything in this context
Photos, videos, images
Anything at all
What is our audience
What is our goal, what are our
references
And then what is the task
And what is the output format
And what is the major things
That you want LLM to focus on
What is the length
And the constraints
And the few short examples
And then the quality checks
Before finalizing
Verify if the email we get
Is in the required requirement
And then quality check
So this is what we call
As a master template prompt
Where you can achieve
Any kind of task
And all this we have built one step
On top of another
This is what prompt engineering
Outside of teaching
There are some agencies
Who are charging 25 to 30 thousand
For teaching prompt engineering
You tell me